<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise in which, is made playne, that Catholikes liuing and dying in their profession, may be saued, by the iudgement of the most famous and learned Protestants that euer were. Agaynst a minister [N.E.] who in his epistle exhorteth an honourable person, to forsake her ancient Catholike Roman Religion, &amp; to become one of his new-found-out Protestant congregation.</title>
            <author>Wright, William, 1563-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15781</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 26044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103083</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838841</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838841</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3230</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15781)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1162:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise in which, is made playne, that Catholikes liuing and dying in their profession, may be saued, by the iudgement of the most famous and learned Protestants that euer were. Agaynst a minister [N.E.] who in his epistle exhorteth an honourable person, to forsake her ancient Catholike Roman Religion, &amp; to become one of his new-found-out Protestant congregation.</title>
                  <author>Wright, William, 1563-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], xvi, [2], 3-32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Permissu superiorum. M.DC.XXIII. [1623]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Wright.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Apparently against the same book or ms. as 26046.5: An epistle dedicated to an honourable person, published in 1622.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through; some leaves cropped at head.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3230:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE TREATISE IN WHICH, Is made playne, that Catholikes liuing and dying in their Profeſſion, may be ſaued, by the Iudgment of the moſt Famous and Learned Proteſtants that euer were. <hi>Agaynſt a Miniſter [N. E.] who in his Epiſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth an Honourable Perſon, to forſake her ancient Catholike Roman Religion, &amp; to become one of his new-found-out Proteſtant Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut. 32. Verſ.</hi> 31.</bibl>
               <p>Et Inimici nostri ſunt Iudices.</p>
               <p>Our Enemies alſo are Iudges.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. M. DC. XXIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3230:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:3230:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE, Contayning certaine Conſiderations, as well for better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the drift of this Treatiſe, as for auoyding all cauills, and anſwearing ſuch Obiections as might be made againſt this Grand Protestant Iury.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Zuinglians are to be nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred (<hi>ſay the Lutherans</hi>) with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Anabaptiſts Nesto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians &amp; Turkes. <hi>And againe.</hi> The Zuingli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans call the Luthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s Eutichians, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwers of many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of faith. <hi>Iezler de Diuturnit. Bell. Euchar. pag. 78. Stancarus.</hi> All the Churches which thoſe men call Reformed by the Ghoſpell and the Sonne of God, &amp; hold the faith of Geneua &amp; Zuricke, concerning Chriſt, are Aria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this he denyed, which I haue aboue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated. <hi>So he. de Trinit. c. 8. Sturmius.</hi> By theſe hatefull diſſentions &amp; peruerſe opinions, the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of our Religion are ouerthrowne, the chiefeſt articles are called in queſtion, many hereſies are brought into the Church of Chriſt, and the high way to Mahometiſme &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme is apparently prepared. <hi>Agayne.</hi> The Lutherans (<hi>ſaith he</hi>) do hold the Proteſtant Caluinian Churches of England, France, Flanders and Scotland for he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall, &amp; their Martyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for martyrs of the diuell. <hi>De ration, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord. ineund. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 2. &amp; 24.</hi>
               </note> FOR the better vnderſtanding of what we are about to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in this Treatiſe; we muſt obſerue firſt, that the maine drift, and ſcope therof, is to ſhew how it is farre better, and more ſecure to liue &amp; dye a Catholike in the Romaine Church, then a Proteſtant in what Congregation ſoeuer: not only becauſe one of them doth <hi>condemne</hi> the other for Schiſmatickes, and Heretikes as vncapable of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; but alſo becauſe Catholickes doe neuer affirme that Proteſtants liuing and dying Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans may be ſaued: not for want of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:3230:3"/> in Catholickes (as ſome doe cauill) ſeing they deſire nothing more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaluation of all, but for want of true faith in Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, without the which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God. whereas Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts doe not deny, that comfort to any vertuons Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Catholike: ſo that for the ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or that brea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (ſaith D. Whyte amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs Proteſtants) <hi>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth ſome particular me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in matters not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erning f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yth</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pag. 13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the booke of Articles. Willet Antilog pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5. 20. D Georg Abbot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Hill. p. 101. 102. D. Doue. <hi>In matters of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we all agree.</hi> Perſuaſ p. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And if they do not agree in on faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> they be the true Church which is but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, &amp; hath only <hi>one Lord, one Faith, one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme?</hi> Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntic. 6. 8. <hi>My doue is one,</hi> Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Conſtant<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e holy, Catholy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>, and Apoſtolicall Church.</hi> Cal. l 4 inſt. c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. See Suarez diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de Ecc Sect. 4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. de fide, ſpe &amp;c.</note> Catholickes, we haue not only the beliefe of Catholickes themſelues, but alſo the iudgement of moſt Famous and Learned Proteſtants, who teach the ſame, eyther expreſſely, or at leaſt in ſuch tearmes, as with the help of their owne brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with whom they are ſayd to <hi>agree,</hi> at leaſt in all materiall points, may ſufficiently be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and in this ſenſe are to be vnderſtood the verdicts of all thoſe which may ſeeme not to be ſo full, and ſufficient as the other in this Grand Proteſtant Iury. As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Zanchius</hi> and other Proteſtants af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that the Roman Church, as yet is the Church of God. Here in expreſſe words is not auerred, that thoſe who liue, and die well in this Church may be ſaued, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe according to the common do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Catholikes doth plainly inough imply the poſſibility of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all thoſe who are members of ſuch a Church. For if they cannot be ſaued in the Church of God, which is <hi>but one,</hi> where els ſhould they ſeeke for theyr ſaluation? Or if they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:3230:3"/> but be damned in the Church of God,<note place="margin">M. Cartright. <hi>I doubt not but diuers fathers of the Greeke Church who were great Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trones of Free-will, are ſaued.</hi> M. Sparke, diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the honoring of Saints Reliques &amp; prayer for the dead, ſaith, <hi>VVe are not ſo haſty to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any for ſuch errors.</hi> Acontius, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Reall preſence<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Both thoſe that deny it, and thoſe that doe hold it, are in the way of Saluation.</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> D. Luther writeth thus: <hi>Bread &amp; wyne are not in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, but the shewes or accidents of bread and wyne: for the bread is changed into the true and naturall body of Chriſt, &amp; the wyne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the true and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bloud of Chriſt.</hi> Serm. de Euch. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerninge receauing vnder one or both kinds, there is no commaundment, ſaith D. Luther. Concerning the Pope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Supremacy, <hi>about it</hi> (ſaith D. Luther) <hi>he is to be borne with all.</hi> Melancton teacheth, how his <hi>Monarchy is profitable.</hi> Concerning Satisfaction. <hi>It was an error in the holy Fathers</hi> (ſaith D. Whitaker) <hi>yet notwithſtanding they were good men and holy Fathers. Did not Iohn H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe that worthy Champion of Chriſt</hi> (ſaith M. Francis Iohnſon) <hi>&amp; other martyrs of foretymes, heare &amp; ſay Maſſe euen to their dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g day &amp;c. Did not alſo diuerſe of them acknowledge, ſome the Popes calling an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Supremacy, ſome 7. Sacraments, ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uricular Confeſsion?</hi> And Benedict Morgenſtern. <hi>Theſe things were pardonable in the Godly who held the Pope to be the Vicar of Chriſt, and head of the Church, the Papacy for the Church, Saintes for mediators, and the Maſſe for the Supper of the Lord.</hi> See the Proteſt. Apol. pag. 471. &amp; 684. You may find aboue three ſcore pointes of Catholicke Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, taught by le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arned Proteſtants, through all the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth Section.</note> how doth ſuch an aſſembly deſerue to be ſtiled the Church of God, and not rather the Synagogue of Sathan? But if <hi>Zanchius</hi> or any other call, the Church of Rome the Church of God, although it haue ſome damnable errous, which hinder the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors therof from their ſaluation; I hope by clearing thoſe imagined errours from being any ſuch barres, out of <hi>Zanchius</hi> his owne learned brethren, euery one may inferre, that <hi>Zanchius</hi> with the help of his brethren Proteſtants, affoardeth ſaluation to all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, liuing well, and dying in the Church of Rome. The helps which we haue out of learned Proteſtants be theſe: To wit that neyther the beliefe of free will, prayer to ſaints, the reall preſence, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, receauing vnder one or both kinds, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images, the Popes ſupremacy, and the monarchy of the B. of Rome, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, merit of good workes, priuate Maſſe, ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or any ſuch taught by the Roman Church, doe hinder any from being capable of their ſaluation: not only becauſe they were all belieued of the holy Fathers, who notwithſtanding the
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:3230:4"/> belief of them haue been reputed alwayes Saints; but becauſe diuers famous learned Proteſtants, brethren to all theſe Iury<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> men, teach the ſame expreſſely: whoſe names you may read in the margent, and what they ſay more largely in the Proteſtants Apology pag. 471 684. &amp;c. Which being applyed to what want ſoeuer occurreth in the verdicts of any named in the Iury, will make it cleare, that no ſuch can be any impediment wherefore the ſame verdict ought not to paſſe, as currant and good. And therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either <hi>Zanchius, Mornay, Serauia,</hi> or any other of theſe Iurers doe accuſe the Church of Rome of Adultery, committing Idolatry, bringing vp children to the diuell, or of any ſuch villanyes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true faith, for belieuing any of theſe points now rehearſed; we muſt tell them in plaine words, that theſe be noe ſuch letts as they imagine, but rather their owne falſe and forged crimes, meere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes, and calumniations put vpon the Church of Rome to make her odious to the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, or for ſome other baſe end:
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:3230:4"/> ſeing their owne brethren confeſſe againſt them, ſaying, that the beliefe of theſe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not eyther hinder their ſanctity, or debarre any Catholike from obtayning their chiefeſt good, and euerlaſting ſaluation; which if they had iudged to be Hereſies, Idolatries, and ſuch like abominations, it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed they would neuer teach.<note place="margin">Calu. l. 4. c. 1. n. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2. Againe, we muſt obſerue with M. Caluin, <hi>that there hath been no tyme ſince the creation of the world, wherin the Lord hath not had his Church, and that there shalbe alſo no tyme to the very end of the world wherin he ſhall not haue it.</hi> But now as for the Church of Rome it is certaine that it did continue the true viſible church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt vntil the tyme of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> as M. <hi>Caluin</hi> hereafter auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: and that from <hi>Constantine</hi> vntill the tyme of <hi>Luther</hi> it neuer was interrupted is<note place="margin">M. Napier vpon the Reuelations. page 145. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 163. 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 237.</note> witnes M. Napier, who ſaith, that <hi>from the yeare 316. God withdrew his viſible Church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the open aſſemblies, to the harts of particular godly men, during the ſpace of 1260. yeares. The Pope and his Cleargy hauing poſſeſſed the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward viſible Church of Chriſtians euen 1260. years, the true Church abyding ſo long latent &amp; inuiſible:</hi> out of which we inferre that all whoſoeuer haue been ſaued ſince Chriſts Church was erected, and ſufficiently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lged, haue beene ſaued in the Roman Church: and whoſoeuer haue dyed as
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:3230:5"/> members cut off from her, or out of her, could neuer attaine to the hopefull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calu. l 4. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. D. Whitaker.</hi> Out of the Church there is no other ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, but the ſeate of error &amp; peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and euerlaſting deſtruction.</note> of their chiefeſt good; but miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of their ſaluation could not auoide to be damned. For what M. <hi>Caluin</hi> deliuereth ſpeaking of the viſible Church is moſt true, to wit: <hi>That out of her lappe no remiſsion of ſinnes is to be hoped, nor any ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at all.</hi> But<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Milius.</hi> If Luther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad bad orthodoxall fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> there had byn no need of a Lutheran reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. Confeſſ. Aug. art. 17. Luther ſaith,</hi> we dare boaſt that Chriſt was firſt publiſhed by vs. <hi>Epiſt. ad Arge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. M. Iewell,</hi> Luther &amp; Zwinglius were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed of God to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle againe the light which you had q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. <hi>Defenſ. Apol. part. 1 c. 7. diuiſ. 3. pag. 56. Pareus.</hi> In Conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes time the Church begun to waxe fick to death, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the Catholike Church remained. But where? In the deſert, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> withdrawne from the eyes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. <hi>lib. 4. de gratia &amp; lib. arb.</hi>
               </note> that there was neuer any other viſible Church of God, which hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued ſince Chriſts tyme, but the Church of Rome, with her adherents, the Proteſtants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues confeſſe. For although ſome fondly i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine, that they had a Church; yet nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Luther</hi> nor <hi>Caluin,</hi> nor any other could euer point any ſuch out, which was appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent or viſible to the eye of men. For who can truly name any one Lutheran before <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> or any one Caluiniſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iohn Caluin?</hi> Verily none: and much leſſe a continuall, and neuer-interrupted ſucceſſion of Lutherans, or Caluiniſts ſince Chriſts tyme, who were not as inuiſible to the world, and as vnknowne as euer were thoſe who are as yet vnborne. A moſt fooliſh thing then it is, yea and moſt ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to auow that indeed there were ſuch a company of zealous Proteſtants, as ſome are not aſhamed to ſay, and that for aboue a thouſand yeares they were all latent and inuiſible: which not only is impious, and
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:3230:5"/> contrary to the Maieſty of the glorious<note place="margin">
                  <hi>VVho will not ſay that it was a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Church that had ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beginning, nor ending, no def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nder, no reprouer, no mouth to vtter, or ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> to heare it, nor pen to write, nor place to rest in.</hi> So M. Iewell in a like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Art. 2. diuiſ. 8. S. Auſtin, <hi>VVhat is this thou ſayeſt? The Church to haue peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed in all Nations, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as to this end the Ghoſpell is preached, that it may be in all Nations? Therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the end of the world the Church i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in all Nations, and this is the ſhortnes of her dayes.</hi> In Pſal. 101. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe Markes</hi> (ſayth D. Willet) <hi>cannot be abſent from the Church: and it is no longer a true Church the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath theſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. For the only ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of them doth make a nullity of the Church.</hi> In his Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ. pag. 69. &amp; 71. which not to haue bene among Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, for aboue a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>000. yeares wil witnes M. Nappier: but in ſome faſhion to haue byn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the Church of Rome is granted by M. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny in his Verdict: which faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue bene the right and true faſhion, is euinced from thence, that otherwiſe the Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch had periſhed, contrary to Chriſts prediction ſaying, <hi>The gates of Hell shall not preuayle againſt it.</hi> M. Caluin lib. 4. inſt. c. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. Cal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4. inſt. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> If God did intend that the Couenant ſhould remayne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable, &amp; left Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme a teſtimony therof for Catholike children, as heere M. Caluin doth inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate; how doth no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Couen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to this day remayne among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Church of Rome? Agayne, if the fayth of Catholick pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts be ſufficient to place their children in the Couen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t &amp; ſtate of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; how much more may it be thought to eſtabliſh the parents themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in that Couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in whom reſide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that faith, which is ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren? Moreouer, if the foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Church halfe caſt down doth remaine amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Catholicks, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> M. Caluin teacheth, which is the true faith &amp; doctrine of Chriſt 1. cor. 3. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. who dare deny that they are in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, or that they may not be ſaued, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they build there vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wood, hay, &amp; ſtubble, at leaſt by fyre, ſeing this is the expreſſe doctrine of the Apoſtle?</note> Kingdome of Chriſt foretould by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; but lykewiſe quite oppoſite to that which they giue out of the eſſentiall notes, and markes of their church, which is the pure preaching of the Word, and the true adminiſtration of the Sacraments: which to make inuiſible were rather to be thought the dreames of mad men, and bedlams, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſolid and ſound doctrine of ſuch great Rabbins and Doctors, who for their ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vertue &amp; learning would rather be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted wiſe Sages by the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, yea &amp; to be ſtiled Reformers forſooth, and that of the true church of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, that <hi>if there be no entry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to lyfe, vnleſſe</hi> (as M. Caluin ſaith) <hi>the viſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h like a Mother conceaue vs in her wombe, vnles she bring vs forth, vnles she feede vs with her breaſts, finally vnles she keepe vs vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der custody, and gouernment vntill ſuch tyme as be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng vncloathed of mortall fleſh, we ſhalbe like vnto Angels;</hi> and noe other viſible church can be aſſigned ſince chriſts tyme but the church of Rome, as we haue ſeen: we muſt needes inferre, that as all whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer haue been ſaued hitherto, for all that
<pb n="viii" facs="tcp:3230:6"/> tyme, were members of the Romaine church; euen ſo all thoſe who deſire to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue to the happy haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Heauen hereafter, muſt liue well, &amp; dy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in that church; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they are neuer like to be partakers of that vnſpeakable ioy, which is the ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their owne ſoules, and to liue with God for euer.</p>
            <p>3. Herehence for better vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of <hi>M. Caluin</hi> his verdict, ſaying, <hi>When God hath left his Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nant in France Ita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, Germany, Spayne, England, ſince theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inces haue byn oppreſſed with the tyrany of Antichriſt (whom he ſayth is the Pope ſitting in the Church of God) yet that this Couenant might remayne inuio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> firſt he there preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued baptiſme the teſtimony of his Couenant;</hi> we gather that the Verdict which is ſet downe for him, to wit, that the Couenant of God hath remayned with them inuiolable, to be moſt true; for ſeing according to that of <hi>M. Caluin,</hi> all thoſe who were hitherto ſaued, could not attayne their ſaluation but in the viſible Church, which was and is only the Church of Rome, as we haue ſeene out of M. <hi>Nappier;</hi> it followeth, that in her the Couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God could not but be kept in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable. Againe, if the Couenant of God was to be kept inuiolable in any company, eſpecially in that which is the Church of
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:3230:6"/> Chriſt, the Sanctuary and Temple of God;<note place="margin">Serauia alſo wil help M. Caluins Verdict who ſaith, <hi>That the Couenant of God to this day doth remaine in the latyn Church.</hi> In defenſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> l. de gratia Miniſt. pag. 31. As concerning the baptizing of the ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Catholiks &amp; how they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned within the Couenat. Se the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Apol. Tract 1. Sect. 6. p. 172. 173. &amp; 174. M. Caluin. <hi>It is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called Catholicke or Vniuerſall, becauſe we cannot find two or three Churches, but that Chriſt muſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> torne in ſunder which cannot be done. l. 4. c. 1. n. 2. But betwixt the yeare of Christ 300. &amp; 316. the Antichriſtian &amp; Papiſticall raigne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n, raigning vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally, &amp; without any debatable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for 1260. yeares</hi> (laſt paſt before Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) So M Napp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er vpon the Reuel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. 37. pag. 68. And no other can be aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned to haue had this vniuerſality, &amp; therfore ſhe is the only true Church of Chriſt.</note> but M. <hi>Caluin</hi> enobleth the church of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me with all theſe titles, &amp; therfore we may well conclude in his iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of God was kept inuiolable in the Church of Rome.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, if Antichriſt who is the Pope according to <hi>Caluin,</hi> doth ſit in the Church of God, or which is all one, in the Church of Rome, of the which the Pope is head, &amp; the church of God be but <hi>One,</hi> as himſelf auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth; it cannot but follow that eyther the Couenant is kept inuiolable in the church of Rome, or no where: but to ſay it was kept no where, cannot be but moſt abſurd, and therfore the other muſt of neceſſity be moſt true, to wit, the Verdict ſet down out <hi>M. Caluin,</hi> that the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t remayneth with them, that is, with the catholikes, and that inuiolable. Neyther can any auoyd this by obiecting, that <hi>Caluin</hi> doth not ſo much ſay that the Church, as the ruines therof, and it half throwne downe, are ſeene vnder the Pope: for ſo the church of chriſt ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> had fallen, and the truth had lyed, ſaying, <hi>The gates of Hell ſhall not preuayle a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt it.</hi> And againe, neither the <hi>Luthera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> nor the <hi>Caluinists</hi> could be members of the true church: for the whole is fallen, and
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:3230:7"/> the ruins of the church half thrown down, is among the Papiſts vnder Antichriſt: if they ſay, they haue a new building; in that it is new, it is not chriſts: and who ſeeth not that it is better to be in the church of chriſt half pulled downe, then in none; ſeeing that ther is kept the couenant inuiolable, or els no were. To this we add, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſayth not, that Antichriſt ſhall ſit in the ruines, or rubbiſh of the church; but abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutly he ſhall ſit in the Temple of God: if the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Temple of God be the true church as other Proteſtants ſay, and that in it he ſhall ſit, that is, he ſhall raigne and gouerne as the head in the true church; how the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can the aſſemblies of Lutherans or caluiniſts be the true church? ſeing Antichriſt ſhall not ſit and dominiere in this? or how can the couenant be inuiolably kept in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in the church of Rome, which is only the true church? We conclude ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that out of caluins Doctrine with the help of his brethren, his Verdict is moſt certayne, to wit, that the couenant of God hath remayned with the catholikes inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olable, yea and in her only, and no where els, as is proued.</p>
            <p>4. Laſtly we muſt obſerue about the Verdict of <hi>Pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſey Mornay,</hi> which as I find in him ſpeaking of the church of Rome, is this.
<pb n="xi" facs="tcp:3230:7"/> 
               <hi>We deny her not the name of Church, no more</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mornay de Eccl. c. 2. As M. Caluin did proue the Church of Rome to haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the true faith of Chriſt, with three groſſe lyes. ſaying that the Popes haue taught three grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous errors, to wit. <hi>That there is no God, no Chriſt, no Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:</hi> Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo Pleſſey Mornay following his Father Caluin, tells vs, that the Church of Rome is an Adultreſſe, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall and bringer vp of children for the diuell. Se Caluin. l. 4. inſt. c. 7. n. 27.</note> 
               <hi>then the name of a man to a man, ſo long as he is aliue though he be neuer ſo ſick yea we are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Spouſe, in as much as she makes a part of the viſible Church, ſo as they will ſuffervs vvithal to call her an adultreſse. But we ſay ſhe is the moſt heretical Church of all thoſe that e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er were: a ſpouſe that prouoked God to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorce her a mother that bringeth vp children for the Diue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> That which Pleſſey Mornay here ſaith in the commendatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church of Rome we willingly admit, and haue ſet it downe for his Verdict: perſwading our ſelues that he could ſay no leſſe truth, which is more forcible then either rack, or torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lling him therunto. For otherwiſe no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willingly lyeth to his owne ſhame; nor freely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth that which ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his owne cauſe. But what he vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth againſt the Church of Rome, for being accurſed and anathematized by her, for ſo many errors and hereſies, both in <hi>Luther</hi> &amp; <hi>Zuinglius,</hi> and other old rotten hereticall<note place="margin">Se F. Perſons Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Triall, with his defence therof a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pleſſy, and O. E by N. D. <hi>Semel mendax ſemper praeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mitur mendax.</hi> Gloſſa. Admitten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in l. Si cui crimen §. 1. ff. de Accuſation. Alciat. &amp; Menoch.</note> Rake-hells of former times, we cannot ſo eaſily belieue; but rather think the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then notorious vntruthes, and meere ſlaunders, as proceeding from him who had a great talent in this black Art of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; which publickely was made knowne to his eternall ſhame by cardinall <hi>Perone,</hi>
               <pb n="xii" facs="tcp:3230:8"/> before the moſt Chriſtian King and Court<note place="margin">Luther. <hi>VVhoſoeuer is once taken in a lye, know moſt certainly that he is not of God but ought to be ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in all thinges.</hi> In Aſſert. Teuton. art. 25. But Pleſſy Mornay was conuinced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in 9. one day, and the exception that the Cardinall tooke agaynſt him did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne 4000. as is to be ſeene in the rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aboue cyted. <hi>The Diuell hath his Prophets</hi> (ſaith Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ullian) <hi>whoſe badg &amp; mark is falſity &amp; ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo that it muſt of neceſsity fall, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is built vpon ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ground.</hi> de praeſcr. c. 40.</note> of France; and therfore we purpoſely haue forborne to diſgrace the Iury with any ſuch foule and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thy ſtuffe, as he ſetteth downe in the latter part of his ſentence, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>it is folly</hi> (ſayth his learned Brother Vorſtius) <hi>to bring in the guilty as vvitneſses in their ovvne cauſe,</hi> or rather to bring in one that hath byn condemned, not once, but ſo often, to rage, rayle, and lye, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt his true and lawfull Iudge, but alſo againſt many other Catholickes, Pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, Princes, Kings and Emperours, who all according to Pleſſey, ſhould haue byn bred and borne baſtards by an Adultreſſe, and brought vp children Idolatours by an hereticall harlot for the Diuell. But (o my Pleſſey) I pray thee how could ſhe be an Adultreſſe, againſt whom Hell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gates were foretold neuer to preuayle? or how could that Church be Hereticall, which neuer was condemned eyther by any lawfull ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, or prouinciall Councell? or by any other iuſt commanding power? or how could ſhe bring vp children to the Diuell, or be an Idolatreſſe, who hath brought vp all to God, that euer were brought to him ſince the firſt erecting of the Church of Chriſt, as we haue ſhewed before. Theſe then are your malicious imputations, and
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:3230:8"/> not thoſe glorious tytles beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming Chriſts vnſpotted Spouſe, and her, who hath byn accompted alwayes the ſacred Sanctuary, and the holy Temple of the liuing God. And therfore deteſting your impieties, we muſt rather giue eare and harken to that holy Byſhop and glorious Martyr S. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian,</hi> who ſpeaking of the Church wryteth<note place="margin">S. Cyprian de vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Eccl.</note> thus. <hi>One Mother</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>there is by the fecundity of her iſsu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> copious and fertile: by her increaſe vve are borne, vvith her milk vve are nouriſhed, we are animated with her ſpirit. The Spouſe of Christ cannot play the aduoutreſse, ſhe is imaculate and vndefiled, ſhe knoweth one houſe, ſhe keepeth with chast baſhfulnes the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of one bedd. This Church preſerueth vs in God, this aduanceth to the Kingdome the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhe hath brought forth: whoſoeuer deuided from the Church, cleaueth to the aduoutreſſe, is ſeparated from the promiſes of the Church.</hi> To whom we add S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> the greateſt of all the Fathers and worthyeſt Deuine the Church of <hi>God euer had ſince the Apoſtles,</hi> if we may belieue D. Field; who is ſtyled lykewiſe the <hi>mouth of antiquity</hi> by other Proteſtants, giuing vs this wholſome Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell againſt all ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch ſlaunderers of the church of Rome. For writing againſt the<note place="margin">S. Aug. tom. 7. de vnitate Eccleſ. c. 11.</note> lyke lies of the Donatiſts, <hi>I know</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>what is written in the holy and Canonicall
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:3230:9"/> Scriptures concerning the Church of Rome; &amp; the fayth therof, I know not what you ſay of her Apoſtacy, or falling from her faith. Truly as we doe read in bookes, the which you alſo doe honour and reuerence, of the Roman Church, and fayth therof: So alſo read you out of Bookes vnto vs, the which we alſo doe honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, how she forſooke and loſt her fayth. Doth it pleaſe you, that we ſhould belieue euery ſlaunderous reproach of men vpon what occaſion ſoeuer it was vttered and obiected againſt the Roman Church, the which the Holy Ghoſt hath both deliuered, and commended vnto vs by his holy Scriptures? This indeed is pleaſing to you; but whom it should more iustly pleaſe, you ſee well inough: but you being ouercome by obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy will not yield to the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We therfore being about to looke as well into the true doctrine and verity, as into the holines and purity of this Church, from whence doth proceed the ſecurity of liuing and dying well in her lappe; we are to vſe the teſtimonies eſpecially of Famous Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, to the end the banners of her glorie may be carryed about, and diſplayed by the penns, and mouthes of our Aduerſaries; that all whoſoeuer are not maliciouſly be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, may therby extoll and magnify the infinit goodnes of Gods prouidence, who hath made, as we may ſay, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enemies of his
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:3230:9"/> Church, and children, although otherwiſe partiall witneſſes, with open mouth to cry out and blaze abroad in effect, <hi>That this is the ſeed, and familie of Ieſus Christ, whom our Lord hath bleſſed:</hi> yea and hath made the<note place="margin">S. Cyprian. l. 1. ep. 3.</note> holy Ghoſt to inſpire the ancient Fathers to warrant vs, that this is the Church <hi>to</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Hierom. l. 3. Apol. contra Ruffin.</note> 
               <hi>which misbeliefe can haue no acceſſe; which receaueth no forgery; and though an Angell</hi>
               <note place="margin">S Cyril. apud D. Thom. in catena.</note> 
               <hi>teach otherwiſe, then hath byn once preached, guarded with S. Pauls authoritie, it cannot be changed; which remayneth vnſpotted from</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Gregor. Nazianz in carm. de vita ſua.</note> 
               <hi>all ſeducing and hereticall circumuention; which hath the true fayth, euen from the tymes of our for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>athers; &amp; alwaies remayneth as is fit for a citty, that ruleth the whole world, to haue euer more a ſound fayth to God.</hi> Out of all which we may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, that this is that bleſſed Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of holy ones, that houſhold of ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctity, that ſpouſe of chriſt, &amp; church of the liuing God, which is the <hi>Pillar and ground of truth,</hi> whoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may boldly imbrace, whoſe directions we may ſafely follow, &amp; reſt ſecurely in her iudgments, as in that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſociety, the which for this 1600. yeares hath yielded vp all thoſe bleſſed Soules of the Apoſtles, Martyrs, Confeſſors, Virgins, and of all the reſt to God, which now do raigne moſt gloriouſly with Ieſus Chriſt the King of glory in Heauen. This
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:3230:10"/> being ſo ſet downe, let vs proceed to the lury.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Faultes to be corrected.</head>
            <p>In the title of the Preface, <hi>all cauills,</hi> read, <hi>ſome cauills.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 8. lin. vlt. <hi>Subbs.</hi> read <hi>Stulbs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 14. lin. 2. humble. more humble.</p>
            <p>Pag. 18. lin. 23. name of a man, as, <hi>read</hi> name of a man to a man, as &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Pag. 25. in the margent, <hi>adde, Luth. declarat. quorumdam artic.</hi> cited by <hi>Coccius</hi> tom. 1. lib. 7. Theſauri pag. 855.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3230:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3230:11"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3230:11"/>
            <head>A GRANDE IVRY Of moſt famous and learned Proteſtants, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all Catholiques of their Saluation, if they liue and dye well, in the Catholique Roman Fayth and Church.</head>
            <list>
               <head>The Names of the Iury Men.</head>
               <item>D Luther.</item>
               <item>M Caluin.</item>
               <item>D. Whitaker.</item>
               <item>D. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ell.</item>
               <item>D. Morton.</item>
               <item>M. Hooker.</item>
               <item>Zanchius.</item>
               <item>Scluſselburg.</item>
               <item>Polanus.</item>
               <item>Iunius.</item>
               <item>Boyſwell.</item>
               <item>Bunny.</item>
               <item>Pleſsis Mornay.</item>
               <item>Serauia.</item>
               <item>D. White.</item>
               <item>D. Willet.</item>
               <item>Sir Edwin Sands.</item>
               <item>M. Stubbs.</item>
               <item>M. Holynſhed.</item>
               <item>D. Godwin.</item>
               <item>M. Cambden.</item>
               <item>Crentremius.</item>
               <item>Theater of great Brit.</item>
               <item>M. Fox.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E ſuppoſe as graunted out of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 1. Act.</hi> 18. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Apoſtles, that the Church of Rome was once the true Church of God and ſo to haue continu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d for diuers hundred yeares, as the Proteſtants themſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3230:12"/> For</hi> M. Iewell <hi>would haue vs belieue:</hi> That as well Saint Auguſtine, as alſo other godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers<note place="margin">Iewell in his Reply to M. Harding pag. 246.</note> rightly yielded reuerence to the Sea of Rome &amp;c. for the purity of religion which was preſerued there a long time without ſpot. See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was a thing notorious (<hi>ſayth M. Caluin</hi>) and without doubt, that after the Apoſtles age<note place="margin">Caluin in his Inſtit. in french lib. 4. ſect. 3. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant. Apol. pag. 210.</note> vntill theſe times (<hi>to wit of Saint Auguſtine</hi>) no change was made in doctrine, neither at Rome nor at any other Cittyes, <hi>which was 440. yeares after Chriſt But D. Morton confirming M. Iewells chalenge auerreth,</hi> that proteſtants in oppugning<note place="margin">D. Mort. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale lib. 4. c. 30. pag. 573. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>74.</note> doctrines which they cal new, and not Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, are ſo far off from ſuffering the limitation of the firſt 440. yeares, that they giue the ſcope of the firſt 600. years; <hi>within the compaſſe of which Saint Gregory liued, who ſent Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Augustine the Monke into England: and therefore he acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth that,</hi> the Pagan and Heatheniſh people by the light of the Ghoſpell through the Miniſtery of Auguſtin, the Legate of Saint Gregory were brought into the fold of Chriſt. <hi>And heerehence ſayth B. Morton</hi> our authours called it a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note place="margin">Morton lib. 1. pag. 60.</note> conuerſion. <hi>But now this being ſuppoſed that the Church of Rome was the true Church for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages togeather, in the which ſaluation was to be had: It remayneth that we demonstrate and ſhew, how not only then but alſo euer after that time euen vnto this day, that Church hath been the only Arke and ſanctuary, in the which whoſoeuer haue liued and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3230:12"/> dyed well, could not miſcary nor miſſe of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that therefore there is no reaſon why a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny being a member of that Church ſhould leaue it and be take himſelfe to any other aſſembly or Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeeing there is but one true Church, and that in her ſaluation can be obteyned, and in all others no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but damnation is to be expected Which we will endeauour to proue out of the testimonies of moſt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bale likewiſe ſayth. <hi>That Auguſtin was ſent from Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory to ſeaſon the Engliſh with the Popiſh faith &amp; that King Ethelbert dyed one &amp; twenty yeares after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> had receaued Popery.</hi> Cent. 1. fol. 3. M. Napiere. <hi>The Pope with his Clergy ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuffered for the ſpace of a thouſand yeares after Silueſter the firſt, any to be ſeene vouchable or viſible of the true Church. pag.</hi> 239. Holynſhed in the Hiſtory of England.</note> 
               <hi>graue and learned Protestants. Suppoſing out of</hi> Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Bede, <hi>that</hi> Saint Auguſtine <hi>was ſent by</hi> S. Gregory <hi>to this our Nation, to conuert it aboue 1000. yeares ſince, from Paganiſme to Chriſt. For theſe be his words.</hi> Saint Auguſtine coming into England, deliuered his errand to King Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert ſaying, he came from Rome, and brought a ioyfull meſſage, which whoſoeuer would obey ſhould haue eternal ioyes, &amp; a perpetuall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with the true and liuing God. <hi>Which is confirmed out of your owne Proteſtant Engliſh Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriographers, and therfore we will begin with their verdicts, and make them as the Formen of this ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, full, and complete Protestant Iury, of whome we will chooſe Holynſhed to be the firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holynſhed therfore ſpeaking of Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine writeth thus.</hi> Auguſtine (<hi>ſayth he</hi>) and his company arriued at Canterbury, where he made his aboad by the Kings permiſſion, exerciſed the life of the Apoſtles, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, cloathing, and prayers, and preaching the word of God to as many as they could, deſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3230:13"/> all wordly pleaſures, as not appertayning to them, receauing only of them whome they taught, things ſeeming neceſſary to the ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their life, all liuing in all points accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the doctrine which they ſet forth. <hi>Item.</hi> At laſt, King Ethelbert was perſwaded by the good example of Saint Auguſtine and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and by miracles ſhewed, to be baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And M. Fox ſpeaking of Saint Augustine, writeth thus.</hi> At length when the King had<note place="margin">Fox lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. 116. of his Acts. &amp;c.</note> wel conſidered the honeſt conuerſation of their life, and moued with their miracles wrought through Gods hands by them, he heard them<note place="margin">
                  <hi>I doubt not but God affoarded many miracles to the firſt in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of our Church.</hi> So D<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Godwin in the life of S. Dauid.</note> more gladly, and laſtly by their holſome exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations &amp; example of good life, he was by them conuerted, and chriſtened in the yeare 596.</p>
            <p>Saint Auguſtine (<hi>ſayth Cambden</hi>) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called the Apoſtle of the Engliſh, ſent hither by Gregory the great, hauing deſtroied the Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters of Hetheniſh impiety with moſt happy ſucceſſe, planting Chriſt in their minds, conuerted them<note place="margin">Cambden in his Britan. pag. 125.</note> to the Chriſtian faith. <hi>Agayne:</hi> Straight vpon the preaching of the name of Chriſt the Engliſh did conſecrate themſelues vnto Chriſt, in ſo feruent a manner, that the diligence is incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, they vſed in the propagation of the name of Chriſt, in the performance of the duties ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, in the diuulging of Chriſtian religion, in building of Churches, in enriching and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſame; that no Prouince of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dome
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3230:13"/> could haue numbred more Monaſteryes then England could in Catholike times: &amp; euen<note place="margin">Fox. pag. 137. That none of all theſe Kings Queenes, Princes, and Prelats were Proteſtants is proued in the prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiall Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and the Proteſtants themſelues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe no leſſe. For M. Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piere ſaith: <hi>That for theſe thouſand two hundred and threeſcore years the Pope &amp; his Clergy hath poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and viſible Church of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, reigning without any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batable contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: Gods truth</hi> (to wit the Proteſtant Church) <hi>moſt certainly abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo long la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</hi> vpon the Reuel. pag. 145.</note> ſome Kings haue preferred religious and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſticall liues before Kingdoms. So many haue been the holy men that England hath brought forth, and which for their moſt firme profeſſion of Chriſtian religion, moſt ſolid conſtancy and ſincere deuotion therin, haue been put into the Kalender of Saints, that in this point it hath not been inferiour to any Chriſtian Prouince whatſoeuer: yea, as Britany was tearmed by Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrius a prophane Philoſopher, <hi>Fer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x Tyranno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum prouincia:</hi> A prouince fertill of Tyrants; ſo likewiſe England may be ſtiled, <hi>Inſula Sancto rum feraciſſima:</hi> An Iland fruitfull of Saints. <hi>So far Cambden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>To whome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e may add another famous Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant author, who tels vs for the tyme past that more Kings and Queenes in England only haue becom'd Monks, and Nunnes, and now by Proteſtants ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured for Saints in heauen, then euer were Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Kings and Queenes in all the world, though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo vnworthy the name of Saints or Sanctity: which are all to be ſeene in the Theater of Britany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn Fox alſo relateth how that eight Kings of England left their Kingdomes and became Monks, whoſe names are theſe:</hi> King Kinegil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, King Cead wall, King Inas, King Ethelred, King Sigebert, King Coenred, King Offa, King Edbert. <hi>Of whome he ſayth, that it is most like they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3230:14"/> did it for holines ſake, thinking in this kind of life to ſerue and pleaſe God better: but in this,</hi> ſayth Fox, <hi>they were deceaued. To theſe we may ioyne 19. Kings &amp; Queenes daughters, whom alſo M. Fox confeſſeth to haue left their Royall estates, and became Nunnes. And he relateth out of an auncient Chronicle that in the primitiue Church of England,</hi> Kings, Princes Dukes, Earles, Barons &amp; rulers of the Churches<note place="margin">Fox lib. 2. pag. 114.</note> incenſed with a deſire of heauen, labouring and ſtriuing among themſelues to enter into Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, into voluntary exile &amp; ſolitary life, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke all and followed the Lord. <hi>And as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerning the piety and deuotion of other Catholiks after, the Centuriſts write thus ſaying:</hi> Although in this age (<hi>to wit the ſeauenth</hi>) the worſhip of God was darkened with mans traditions and ſuperſtitions; yet the ſtudy to ſerue God and to liue godly and iuſtly, was not wanting to the miſerable common people &amp;c. they were ſo at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue to their prayers, as they beſtowed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the whole day therin. They did exhibite to the Magiſtrate due obedience, they were moſt ſtudious of amity, concord and ſociety, ſo as they could eaſily remit iniuries: all of them were carefull to ſpend their time in honeſt vacation and labour: to the poore &amp; ſtrangers they were<note place="margin">Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turiſts. cent. 7. c. 7. col. 181. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubbs in his motiue pag. 43.</note> moſt courteous and liberall; and in their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and contracts moſt true.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Subbs in his Motiue to good works, ſayth.</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:3230:14"/> Certainely, to ſpeake the truth, there is many times found conſcionabler and plainer dealing among moſt of the Papiſts, then amongſt many proteſtants. And if we looke narrowly into the ages paſt, we ſhall find more godliues, deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and zeale, though blind, more loue one to another, more fidelity &amp; faythfulnes euery way in them, then is now to be found in vs. <hi>And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne he further ſayth.</hi> Is it not a ſhame vnto vs<note place="margin">Stubbs in his motiue pag. 72. To name one amongſt many Robert Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelſey the 49. Archb of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury: <hi>Beſids the dayly fragme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> (ſaith Godwin) <hi>of his houſe, he gaue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Friday and Sunday to euery begger a loafe of Bread, &amp; there were euery ſuch Almeſ dayes, foure or fiue thouſand people. Beſides this eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great feſtiuall day, he ſent a 150. pence to ſuch poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as could not fetch his Almes.</hi>
               </note> that our forefathers liuing in the times of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition &amp;c. ſhould ſo far notwithſtanding out paſſe vs in good works, as that we may not once be compared to them in any ſmall meaſure? He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, for good works, who ſeeth not that herin they were far beyond vs, &amp; we far behind them. For exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, what memorable famous buildings, and what monuments haue they left to the world behind them? What Churches, Chappels, and other houſes of prayer did they erect, to the end the Religion and ſeruice of God might be continued? Yea what Monaſteries, Abbyes, Priories, and other religious houſes &amp;c. what number of goodly bridges did they make. How many Almeſ-houſes, Hoſpitalls, and Spittles, did they found &amp;c. What high wayes, what pauements and cauſies? in ſumme what famous Colledges, Hals, &amp; Vniuerſities, what ſchooles? In ſo much as the former Statute of Mort-main (<hi>now needles</hi>) was yet then thought needfull to be made in reſtraint of ſuch liberall deuotion.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:3230:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But to giue ſome tast in particular of thoſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and godly men who liued in theſe times, we will beginne with Saint Dunstone Archbiſhop of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury,</hi> who was moſt gracious to King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and Ethelrede, <hi>as wittneſſeth M. Godwin,</hi> vnder whome he ruled all thinges, at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and for the moſt part admired for a moſt holy &amp; vertuous man, and after canonized for a Saint.</p>
            <p>Saint Elphege <hi>another Arch-biſhop of the ſame ſea, was (ſayth the ſame authour</hi>) of great pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, &amp; of wonderfull abſtinence, neuer ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or drinking nor ſleeping more then neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity<note place="margin">God win i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his life.</note> compelled him, ſpending his tyme altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in piety, ſtudy, or other neceſſary buſines, ſo that with preaching &amp; example of holy life he conuerted many to Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Duke William after his conqueſt made choyce of</hi> Lanfranke <hi>for his wiſdome and faythfulnes to be Arch biſhop of Canterbury,</hi> as one in all reſpects<note place="margin">God win i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his life.</note> moſt fit and worthy. He was the moſt perfect (<hi>ſayth Bale</hi>) of his time in all kind of Logicke or<note place="margin">Bale Centur. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſubtility of Ariſtotle. He corrected &amp; amended according to the right fayth, all the bookes of the old and new Teſtament which had been corrupted by fault of the writers, and alſo the writings of the holy Fathers. He was ſkillfull in ſcience (<hi>ſayth Stow</hi>) prudent in counſells, and gouernement, and for religion and life<note place="margin">Stow. Chron. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>79.</note> moſt holy. He was (<hi>ſayth Godwin</hi>) buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3230:15"/> 
               <hi>Rufus</hi> to vertue and godlines. And as long as Lanfranke liued (<hi>ſayth Stow</hi>) Rufus ſeemed to abhorre all kind of vice, in ſo much that he was counted the mirrour of Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saint Anſelme likewiſe was</hi> a moſt worthy man of great learning, as his workes yet extant do declare, and for integrity of life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation admirable: vndoubtedly he was a good &amp; holy man, and as worthy the honour of a Saint as any I thinke (<hi>ſayth Godwin</hi>) euer was cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized by the Pope ſince his time. None (<hi>ſayth Malmſbury</hi>) liued more obſeruant of Iuſtice,<note place="margin">Malmeb. lib. 4. Regum.</note> None at that tyme ſo ſoundly learned, None ſo wholely ſpirituall, the Father of the countrey &amp; the mirrour of the world.</p>
            <p>Saint Thomas (<hi>ſayth Houeden</hi>) was of life<note place="margin">S. Thomas of Canterbury. Houeden part. 2. Anal.</note> irreprehenſible, he receaued day by day 3. or 5. diſciplines at the Prieſts hands: his inner gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was of rugged haire-cloath of goates haire wher with his whole b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy was couered, from the elbow to the knees: he lay vpon the bare gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>und before his bed, &amp; neuer ceaſed from pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r vntill for very wearines he layd downe his head vpon a ſtone which he there placed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of a boulſter. (<hi>Alſo Fox ſayth</hi>) he was full<note place="margin">Fox Acts. 206. God win in his life.</note> of deuotion: <hi>and Godwin,</hi> that he was moſt ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically elected, and preſently after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration became ſo graue, ſo auſtere, ſo deuout in all outward ſhew, as he ſeemed quite another man. <hi>King Henry the ſecond, his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3230:16"/> voluntary pennance for giuing ſome cauſe, or occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his death, the ſame day was rewarded by a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi>
               <note place="margin">Godwin in vit. Bald win. <hi>They lackt the doctrine &amp; know ledge in Chriſts Ghoſpel, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the arti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle of free iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by faith and therefore</hi> (ſayth Fox) <hi>they ran the wrong way.</hi> Acts. pag 133. And agayne ſpeaking of our ancient Criſtian Kings he vſeth theſe words. <hi>How great the blindnes &amp; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of theſe men was, who wanting no zeale, wanted knowledg, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation by their meritorious deeds: which I write</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>here to put vs in mynd how much we at this preſent are bound to God for the true ſinceerity of his truth, hidden ſo long before to our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anceſtors, &amp; opened now to vs This only lamenting, to ſee them haue ſuch works and want our fayth, and we to haue a right fayth &amp; want their workes. pag.</hi> 133.</note> 
               <hi>Victory agaynſt his enemies. And what deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our Anceſtors had to this Saint may be ſeene by the riches they gaue to his Shryne: of which Shrine Eraſmus relateth,</hi> that the baſeſt part was gold, it all ſhined glittering, and caſt forth lightning by reaſon of the rare and mighty gemmes and pretious ſtones; yea the whole Church in euery part abounded more then with royall riches. And euery one (<hi>ſayth Godwin</hi>) thought himſelfe happy, that could doe any thing to his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But now (as D. Barlow ſayth) although Kinges</hi> haue many occaſions, which may allure them to ſinne, eſpecially hauing that priuiledge in ſcripture, whether <hi>ex gratia,</hi> or <hi>de facto,</hi> whether from exemption from God, or grace of men: that no man may ſay vnto them, Why doe you this? <hi>Yet among our anncient Catholike Kings, haue been ſo many and ſo eminent in all kind of deuotion, holines, and ſanctity as we need not bring in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our preſent purpoſe ſauing only ſome of them ſet downe to haue been ſuch. Yea euen by our owne learned Proteſtant authors. For,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>King Oſwald (ſayth Stow</hi>) with a ſmall ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ouercame the Brittans, and ſlew Ceadwall their King. He ſent for Aidan a Scot to aduance
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3230:16"/> the Chriſtian Religion among his people, gaue him holy Iland for his ſea<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he enlarged his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, reconciled the Deiri &amp; Bernitians which deadly hated one another: he was ſlayne by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gans fighting for his Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try; &amp; at laſt (<hi>ſaith Stow</hi>) was canonized for a Saint<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whoſe faith &amp; deuotion was ſo great (<hi>ſayth Beda</hi>) that he did<note place="margin">Theater pag. 337.</note> ſhine with miracles after his death. <hi>Of this King Oſwalds hand, other Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts write (for being boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull to the poore,</hi>) That after his death it neuer conſumed, but was ſhrined in ſiluer in S. Peters Church at Bedda, now Bambrough, with wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy honour, was worſhipped for the miracles &amp; eures that it did, as likwiſe the earth wheron his bloud was ſpilt.</p>
            <p>King Canutus went on Pilgrimage to<note place="margin">Theater of great Britany. pag. 391. 392.</note> Rome, to viſit the ſepulcher of Saint Peter and Saint Paul, built many Churches and Abbeyes, greatly reuerenced Saint Bennet: he offered vp his crowne vpon the Martyrs Saint Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munds Tombe. Moſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rich and Royall Iewells he gaue to the Church of Wincheſter, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one is recorded to be a Croſſe worth as much as the whole reuenew of England a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted to in one yeare. He ſet his crowne on the head of the picture of our Sauiour on the Croſſe at Wincheſter, neuer wearing it more. Cooper <hi>ſayth, that for</hi> his vertuous life he was<note place="margin">Cooper. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1027.</note> worthy to liue perpetually. He was of great magnificence, and vſed ſuch Iuſtice and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3230:17"/> that in his dayes there was no Prince of renowne, towards God humble and lowly.</p>
            <p>Amongſt al the Saxon Kings hitherto is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d none to be preferred, or almoſt to be compared with Alfred, for the great and ſingular qualities in this King worthy of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gh renown, <hi>ſayth Fox,</hi> whether we behould his valiant acts and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold trauells for his Countrey, or his godly and excellent vertues ioyned with a publike &amp; ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der care of the weale publike, or whether we<note place="margin">Bale cent. cap. 43. Cambd. pag. 444. Malmesb. lib<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. c. 4. Weſtm. An. 892. 871.</note> reſpect his notable knowledge of good letters with a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſire to ſet forth the ſame throgh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all his Realme. He fought (<hi>ſayth Bale</hi>) 57. tymes with the Danes, &amp; according to <hi>Camb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en</hi> repreſſed them at his pleaſure. He wrote &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgated moſt Chriſtian lawes, &amp; cauſed ſuch peace, as he made bracelets of gold to be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp in the high way which none durſt touch. He day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hard Maſſe &amp; ſayd his houres &amp; Matins, &amp; in the night ſeaſon vnknowne to all his ſeruants he frequented Churches to heare ſeruice. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring beautifying and enriching monaſteries he laboured earneſtly, among which he built<note place="margin">See Fox. pag. 142.</note> two of great renowne: he was crowned and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed by Pope Leo, &amp; was tearmed his adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue child, <hi>ſayth M. Bale: to whome S. Cuthbert</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox. Acts. lib. 3. p. 154.</note> 
               <hi>appeared when he was in distreſſe, aſsuring him that he ſhould ouercome the Danes, as he did indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King Edgar (<hi>ſayth Fox</hi>) was much giuen to all vertuous &amp; princely acts worthy of much
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3230:17"/> commendation and famous memory, excellent in Iuſtice, maintained the Godly, loued the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, was deuout to God, and beloued of his ſubiects, whome he gouerned in much peace and quietnes. No yeare paſſed in the tyme of his Reygne in which he did not ſome ſinguler and neceſſary commodity for the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.<note place="margin">Houed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n pag. 426.</note> A great maintener of Religion and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arning. He had in readines 3600. ſhips <hi>of warre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and made 8. Kings to row him in a boate he ſitting at</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fox lib. 3. pag. 154. Prud. Ballance pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>31.</note> 
               <hi>the ſterne and guiding it. Moreouer he</hi> was a great patron of Monkiſh religion, builded (<hi>as ſome ſay</hi>) as many Monaſteries as there be Sundayes in the yeare, or as <hi>Edne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>porteth 48. <hi>Saint E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditha was this Kings daugher, who from her infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was brought vp in a monaſtery, and would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cooper an. 975. Stow. p. 113.</note> 
               <hi>that life to enioy the crowne after her brother King Edwards death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cooper and Stow write, how Saint Edward Martyr</hi> was in all kind of honeſt vertues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable to his Father Edgar, began his ſoueraig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity<note place="margin">Fox Acts. pag. 159. Cooper. An. 977. Cambd. Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. pag. 70<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with much modeſty and mildnes, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily fauoured of all: Was a vertuous and noble Prince (<hi>ſayth Fox</hi>) much pitifull and bountifull to the poore: for him (<hi>ſayth Cooper</hi>) after his death God ſhewed many miracles. <hi>Of King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the first Cambden writeth thus.</hi> He was a Prince far excelling, in whoſe moſt valia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mind God choſe a moſt worthy lodging, that he might match the height of Royall Maieſty not
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3230:18"/> only with fortitude and wiſedome, but with beauty alſo and comlines of body, whome For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in the prime flower of his age trayned vp in many warres and moſt difficult times of the Commonwealth, whilſt that ſhe diſpoſed him for the Britiſh Empire: which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in, he ſo gouerned, hauing ouercome the Welch-men and triumphed ouer the Scots, that by good right he is eſteemed another orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Brittany.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King Stephen (ſayth Stow</hi>) was a noble man, and paſſing hardy, of paſſing comely fauour &amp; perſonage, in all Princely vertues he excelled, as in martiall policy, affability, gentlenes, and bountifull liberality towards all. He was very noble in birth (<hi>ſayth Godwin</hi>) but much more in vertue, and all good manners: many miracles (<hi>wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth he</hi>) are ſaid to be wrought at his To<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be. <hi>And this may ſuffice to vnderſtand in ſome manner the holines and ſanctity of our auncient Catholike Kings. But to proceed concerning other famous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, D. Couell writeth thus of Alexander Hales<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> S.</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Couell in defence of Hooker pag. 241.</note> 
               <hi>Bonauenture, and Saint Thomas, all three great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the Roman Church. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d first of Alexander Hales he ſayth,</hi> who made his Summe that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent worke, by commaundement of Pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius the fourth; that he was called the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life, becauſe of that liuely knowledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that flowed from him; he was mayſter of Bona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, a ſcholler not inferiour to himſelfe, of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3230:18"/> whom he was went to ſay, that in Bonauenture he thought Adam ſinned not, meaning of that illumination, which was in him (<hi>and doubtleſſe there was much in him</hi>) as though he had not been darkened by the fall of Adam: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church called him the Seraphicall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour. To theſe Aquinas was not inferior; who came ſo neere vnto Saint Auguſtine; whome in his book agaynſt <hi>Burges</hi> he eſteemeth the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt doctor that euer was, or euer ſhall be excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Apoſtles &amp;c. that ſome thought he had all his works by hart, &amp; by a common prouerbe it was ſpoken, that the ſoule of Saint Auguſtine dwelt in Aquinas, in whome aboue all the reſt, foure contraryeties were ſaid to excell, aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, breuity, facility &amp; ſecurity, in reſpect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he gayned the tytle to be called Angelicall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then if theſe men were the Popes Agents, and yet ſo renowned and glorious, and their doctrine ſo ſecure and excellent, why may not we ſecurely follow them in the ſame ſtepps of Agency in ſuch buſines. Now all this being ſo, it is no wonder if our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are forced to ſet out, magnify, and extoll the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luth. in ep. cont Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt Tom. 2. Germ. fol 267. Where alſo he ſavth, <hi>that vnder the Papacy there are many godly men &amp; great Saints.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Church of Rome, and truely in that manner as they are not affrayde to deliuer their mindes in ſuch tearmes, as Catholikes themſelues could ſcarce deſire or wiſh any better. For herehence</hi> we confeſſe <hi>ſayth D Luther</hi>) that there is vnder the Papacy moſt of Chriſtian good, yea, rather all Chriſtian good, and that from thence it came to vs: Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3230:19"/> we confeſſe, that there is in the Papacy true Scripture, true Baptiſme, the true Sacrament of the Altar, the true keyes to remiſſion of ſinns, the true office of preaching, true Catechiſme; and I ſay further, that there is in the Papacy true Chriſtianity, yea rather the true kernell of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Caluin agaynſt Sadolet.</hi> We do not deny thoſe to be the Churches of Chriſt, in which<note place="margin">Caluin againſt Sadolet pag. 128.</note> you gouerne. <hi>And in the 2. to the Theſſalonians he confeſſeth that,</hi> the papacy is the Temple, yea and the Sanctuary of God: <hi>and elſe where,</hi> that the<note place="margin">Caluin l. 4. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. c. 2. n. 11.</note> couenant of God hath remayned with them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iunius.</hi> All diuine thinges are in the Popes Church, and hitherto it is the Church of God.<note place="margin">Iunius. de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. c 17. col. 1020.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchius.</hi> The Roman Church is yet the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pleſſey Mornay.</hi> The Roman Church is the<note place="margin">Mornay. lib. de Eccle. c. 2. &amp; 10.</note> ſpouſe of Chriſt, as yet not diuerted from him, ſhe is a mother that bringeth forth children to God: the name of the Church is no more to be denyed to her, then the name of a man, as long as he liueth.<note place="margin">Polan. part. 1. Theſ de Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Polanus.</hi> The Roman Church at this day, is yet the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serauia.</hi> The Church of Rome it yet the Church: and ſee what I will ſay more: ſhe is<note place="margin">Serauia in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. lib. de gratia Miniſt. pag. 3.</note> our mother, in the which, and by which God hath regenerated. <hi>And agayne</hi> The Couenant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3230:19"/> of God to this day doth remayne in the Latine Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boyſwell.</hi> I acknowledge the Church of<note place="margin">Boyſ. in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fut. Spon. pag. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. 283. 822.</note> Rome as yet to be in the Couenant of God; yea, ſhe is the Church, the ſpouſe, and the Temple of God; the Church of Ieſus Chriſt redeemed by him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Hooker.</hi> We acknowledge willingly<note place="margin">D. Hooker. l. 3. de Politia Eccleſ. p. 128.</note> them, to wit the Papiſts, to be of the family of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll.</hi> I affirme the members of the<note place="margin">Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. pag. 68.</note> Church of Rome to be members of the true Church of Chriſt, and that thoſe who liue and dye in that Church, may be ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And D. Whitaker doth confeſse,</hi> That a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt<note place="margin">D. Whitaker contro. 4. 9. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> c. 3. p. 682.</note> the Papiſts is a miniſtery, and a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine preaching of the Word, which without doubt to ſome is ſufficient to ſaluation.<note place="margin">D. White in defence c. 7. p. 356. cap. 41. p. 408.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I neuer deemed (<hi>ſayth D. White</hi>) that to be the viſible Church of God, in the which our Aunceſtors held the true fayth, and were ſaued. <hi>And agayne.</hi> We confeſſe, that the Church of Rome in all ages, hath been the viſible Church of God.<note place="margin">Schluſſ tom 8. in catal. Haeret. pag. 434.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scluſselburg.</hi> Luther ſaith that all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an good is in the Popedome; &amp; that from thence it came to vs, we do not deny.<note place="margin">Rhegius in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider. cenſurae pag. 93.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Iohannes Rhegius.</hi> Although it be true that the miniſtery of the Popes was corrupt with many traditions and inuentions of men,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3230:20"/> neuertheleſſe it had thoſe thinges, which were neceſſary to ſaluation, to wit, the Canonicall bookes, the Creed of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leonardus Crentremius.</hi> The Biſhop of<note place="margin">Crentrem. in 1. Cor. 3.</note> Rome doth retaine this ſame ground of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like fayth 1. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 3. the which both I doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with the Catholike and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Church, although in certaine circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces there be ſome diuerſity of opinions.<note place="margin">Zanch. in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. lib. de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Dei.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zanchius.</hi> The Church of Rome in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite of Sathan, did retayne the principal grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of fayth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boyſwell.</hi> We acknowledge that the Church<note place="margin">Boyſwell in Confutatione Sondei p. 79.</note> of Rome is pure in the principall articles of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hooker.</hi> They hould conſtantly, to wit Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,<note place="margin">Hooker lib. 5. de polit. pag. 128.</note> the chiefe parts of the Chriſtian faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D. White,</hi> We agree with the Church of Rome, in ſubſtantiall articles of fayth.<note place="margin">D. White in defence c. 38. 8. 273.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Field.</hi> The Roman and Latine Church continued the true Church of God euen till our tyme. <hi>And agayne:</hi> we doubt not but the Church<note place="margin">D. Field of the Church pag. 282.</note> in which the Biſhop of Rome exalted himſelfe (<hi>he addeth with more then Lucifer-life pride</hi>) was notwithſtanding the true Church of God; that it held a ſauing profeſſion of the truth in Chriſt, and by force thereof conuerted many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes from errour to the way of truth.<note place="margin">D. Willet. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. pag. 144.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D Willet</hi> It is not denyed by any Proteſtant but many renowned Kings and Queens (which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3230:20"/> might not pleade ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Roman Faith) are Saints in heauen. <hi>And ſpeaking of his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. of Engliſh Proteſt. to the King.</note> 
               <hi>mother, he attributeth ſuch holynes and truth to her Religion and her, that it preuayled with God not only for herſelf but her ſonne our Soueraygne al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. His wordes be theſe.</hi> The child of ſuch prayers &amp; teares cannot poſſibly fall away.<note place="margin">Bren. in Apol. pro confeſſ. Wittemb p. 297.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brentius.</hi> We doubt not, but that many haue obteyned true ſaluation in popery. <hi>And ſpeaking of S. Bernard, whom D. Whitaker confeſſeth to haue been a member of the Roman Church, he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Whitak. ad o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio. 7. Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian. p. 30. Caluin. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp; Bernard were holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 4. inſtit. c. 7. n. 22. Lubbertus. we thinke truly that Bernard was a Saint. l. 6. de Eccleſ. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>thus.</hi> I iudge Bernard to haue been a man endewed with great piety and deuotion, and to liue now happily with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop Barlow in his third ſermon,</hi> The lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neder writers do acknowledge the Church of Rome to be the Church of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D. Some agaynſt Penry in diuers places auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>beth,</hi> that Papiſts are not altogeather aliens fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods couenant. That in the iudgement of all learned men, and al reformed Churches there is in Popery a Church, a miniſtery, a true Chriſt. If you thinke that all the Popiſh ſect, which dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Popiſh Church are damned, you think abſurdly, and diſſent from the iudgement of the learned Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>M. Bunny.</hi> The Church of Rome hath<note place="margin">Bunny in his Treatiſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation Sect. 14. pag. 89.</note> euer continued after a ſort in profeſſion of the fayth ſince the time that by the Apoſtles it was deliuered to them &amp;c. and hath in ſome manner
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3230:21"/> alſo preſerued, and hitherto maintayned both the Word and Sacraments that Chriſt himſelfe did leaue vnto vs, which ſurely (<hi>ſayth he</hi>) is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpeciall bleſſing, and an euident worke of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S. Edwin Sands writeth thus of the Roman Church.</hi> There are among them vndoubtedly, in<note place="margin">Sir Edwin ſads in his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. num. 48.</note> great multitude, men, vertuous, learned, fraught with the loue of God, and the truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things, men of memorable integrity of hart &amp; affections. In their Sermons much mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter both of fayth and piety is eloquently deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by men of wonderfull zeale and ſpirit. The outward ſtate and glory of their ſeruice, doth engender, quicken, increaſe, and nouriſh the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward reuerence, reſpect, and deuotion, which is due vnto ſoueraygne maieſty and power. Their deeds of charity are exceeding. No ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of life comparable to ſome of their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. If Proteſtants were, or could be at vnion with them, they ſhall find excellent order of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, ſingular helpes for increaſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines and deuotion, for the conquering of ſinne, for the profiting of vertue.</p>
            <p>Yet in the chiefe of whome they ſend out<note place="margin">Ibid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 25.</note> to preach, in the diligence and paynes which they take in their ſermons, in the ornaments of eloquence and grace of action, in their ſhew of piety and reuerence towardes God, zeale to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the truth, of loue towardes his people,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3230:21"/> which euen with teares they can often teſtify, they match their aduerſaries in the beſt, and in the reſt far exceed them. But heerein the Ieſuits carry the bell from all others, hauing attayned the commendatiom, and working the effect of perfect Orators, of whome in Lent one in each Citty of Italy doth preach euery Day, without intermiſſion, if their ſtrength do ſerue them, ſo as ſix dayes in the weeke they preach on the Ghoſpell of the dayes, and on the Saturday in honour and praiſe of our Lady. So euery yeare changing their preacher, there is the delight of variety, and in the daily continuing of the ſame the admiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of induſtry. Some ſuch like courſe it is to be thought the Ieſuites hold alſo in other Countreys, their proiects being certaine &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly purſued. But wonderfull is the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which redounds thereby to their Order, and exceding the aduantage which giueth to their fide. For bookes of prayer &amp; piety all countreys are full of them at this day in their owne lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage &amp;c. In defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding their doctrine they dare enter into combat with the beſt of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnants and will not doubt either to entangle them ſo, in the ſnares of their owne quirks, or at leaſt wiſe ſo put of his blowes with the word of their diſtinctions, that an ordinary Orator ſhall neuer perceaue them to be vanquiſhed; and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorable Auditor ſhall report them vanquiſhers: whereupon now they cry mainely in all places for triall by diſputations.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3230:22"/>
            <p>Moreouer ſuch is their diligence and dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in inſtructing, that euen the Proteſtants the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues (in ſome places) ſend their ſons to their ſchooles, vpon deſire to haue them proue excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in thoſe artes they teach. This Order hath alſo their ſolemne Cathechizing in their Church on Sundaies, and Holidayes, for all youth that will come, or can be drawne vnto it. But this point of their ſchooles in inſtructing youth is thought of ſuch moment, by men of wiſedome and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being taught ſo by very experience and triall thereof, that the planting of a good Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Ieſuits in any place, is eſteemed the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſure way, to replant that Religion and in time to eate out the contrary. <hi>So far the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Relator.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to proceed from the common multitude of lay people and Eccleſiasticall perſons, to the Popes themſelues, this ſame anthour hath found much ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, deuotion, and piety in thoſe, which haue been in theſe tymes: and of the laſt Pope Clement the 8 he</hi>
               <note place="margin">Relat. of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion n. 42. 43.</note> 
               <hi>writeth thus.</hi> He did often weepe vpon piety &amp; godly compaſſion at his Maſſes, &amp; proceſſions. His eyes were ſtill watering, ſometimes ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with teares, in ſo much that for weeping he ſeemed another Heraclitus He was a good Pope, a good man, a good Prelate, a good Prince. And as for the Lutheranes in Germany<note place="margin">Relation. n 45.</note> they like the Religion of Catholiks ſo well, that both the Clergy and Layty, openly proteſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3230:22"/> they will rather returne to the Roman Church, then ioyne with the Sacramentary and predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary peſtilence. <hi>The Puritans in this Nation, in their late Offer of Conference, preferre the Roman Church far before their Countrey Proteſtants. Of the Proteſtants there will be as little question. And in particular M. Iacob writeth thus.</hi> The Biſhops<note place="margin">M. Iacob. p. 73.</note> of England when they deale with the Puritans muſt ioyne plainely with the Catholiks in their anſwers if they will maintayne themſelues. <hi>So that we ſee in the iudgement of all, both Catholikes, Lutherans, Caluinists, Protestants, &amp; Puritans, that to remayne in the Catholike Church, and to liue and dye in it, is the ſecureſt way to attayne to our chiefest good, and at last to receaue the promiſed reward of our endles happynes, ioy, and euerlasting ſaluation: the which is confirmed by no leſſe a man then D. Luther himſelfe, with whome we will end.</hi> That the Roman Church of God (<hi>ſayth he</hi>) before al others is to be honored, there is no doubt. S. Peter, S. Paul, forty ſix Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Biſhops &amp; ſo many hundred thouſand Martyrs haue ſhed their bloud, &amp; haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Hell &amp; death, that it may euen be felt what a ſingular reſpect God hath to that Church. And if now, alas, the matter ſo goeth at Rome, as it were expedient it went better: yet neither is there, or can be ſo great cauſe, that a ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or departure be made. <hi>Heerehence thoſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi>
               <note place="margin">Offer of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer. pag. 16.</note> 
               <hi>which offered Conference, ſpeaking of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſay.</hi> That if the miniſters (<hi>to wit the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes</hi>)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3230:23"/> be in errour, they proteſt to all the world, that the Pope and the Church of Rome (and in them God &amp; Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe) haue had great wrong and indignity offered vnto them: in that they are reiected, and that all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Churches are Schiſmaticall, in forſaking vnity and communion with them. <hi>And a little before, ſpeaking of ſome poſition among them, offered then to be diſputed,</hi> they write in plaine tearmes, how diuers of the poſitions are ſuch, that if the<note place="margin">Offer of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer. pag. 11.</note> miniſters ſhould not conſtantly hould &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine the ſame againſt all men, they cannot ſee how poſſibly, by the Rules of diuinity the ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our Churches from the Church of Rome, and from the Pope, the ſupreme head therof, can be iuſtified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But now if in the Church of Rome there be true Chriſtianity and Sanctity, yea and the very kernell of Chriſtianity: if ſhe be the Temple and Sanctuary of God, in the which remaynet his Couenant inuiolable and all diuine things. If ſhe be the ſpouſe of Christ, the family of Ieſus Chriſt, and the mother Church conteyning all things neceſsary to ſaluation. If ſhe be the Church in which our Ancestours liued and were ſaued: if ſhe continued alwayes adorned with all kind of Chriſtian good: Enobled with moſt learned, iuſt &amp; godly perſons; fraught with all kind of good workes, of Miracles, piety &amp; deuotion; &amp; if ſhe hath bred more Kings and Queenes Saints then were euer of of thoſe tytles Proteſtants in all the Christian world:
<pb facs="tcp:3230:23"/> and if now to conclude <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re neyther is, nor can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſufficient cauſe wy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould ſeparate themſelues from that Church. If all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> his be true, as Protestants themſelues haue now in this Grand-Iury acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and confeſsed: I do not doubt, but euery one may ſee &amp; perceaue, that whoſoeuer liueth a true me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that Church, and ſtriueth to goe forward in all kind of vertue, may not only be ſaued, but ariue alſo to that degree of holines &amp; perfection, as to become a bleſſed ſoule on earth, and there aboue to be crowned a thrice happy &amp; moſt glorious Saint in heauen. Out of which we may inferre, that whoſoeuer are members of this Church, in the which only ſanctity and ſaluation is to be had, as our Aduerſaries themſelues confeſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ught to auoyde most carefully all ſuch wicked and diabolicall ſuggeſtions, as the enemy of man, by what Miniſter ſoeuer, may put into their heads, to ioyne themſelues to any other congregation: eſpecially ſeing according to M. Caluin,</hi> out of her lappe (to wit<note place="margin">Caluin. l. 4. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. c. 2. n. 4.</note> the viſible Church) no remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins or ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all is to be hoped: for the Lord doth mak ſo great accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of his Church<note place="margin">Caluin. n. 10. For Germany D<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Field ſayth, that <hi>Luther &amp; the reſt of his Religion, were baptized, recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and power of miniſtery in that Church</hi> (to wit of Rome) <hi>as the true v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſible and appa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Church of Chriſt.</hi> D. Field pag. 71. D. Couell in defence of Hooker p 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. For France. Caluin l. 4 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. §. 2. l. 4. <hi>VVe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>haue departed from their Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church.</hi> For England the Apologer pag 188. con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſeth no leſſe ſaying: <hi>we haue indeed gone from the Pope, we haue ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ken of the yoake of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome.</hi>
               </note> as he ſhal be held a trayterous turne-coate, ſaith M. Caluin, and a forſaker of his Religion, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer diſobediently alienates himſelf from that Chriſtian Society. Whence it followeth that a departing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Church is a denying of God &amp; Chriſt, &amp; therfore ſo much the more muſt we beware of ſuch kind of ſeparation or breach of fayth. Seing, neyther can there be a more hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3230:24"/> crime imagined, then with ſacrilegious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſloialty, to violate that wedlocke which the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Sonne of God hath contracted with vs. <hi>So far<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> M. Caluin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pardon vs therfore (good M. Parſon,) if we willingly and conſtantly remayne where we are, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being any thing moued with your trifles &amp; toyes, confuted elſewhere, to change our fayth &amp; profeſſion which we haue been taught alwayes in the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church. And if you haue any care of the chiefeſt good of your ſoules ſaluation, make hast to repayre to vs with your miſerable ſeduced flocke, or otherwiſe reflect ſeriouſly vpon this terrible ſentence of</hi> S. Fulgentius, <hi>who ſayth.</hi> Belieue aſſuredly and doubt nothing, that euery Heretike or Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticke, chriſtened in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, &amp; of the Holy Ghoſt, if he not within the number of thoſe which are of the Catholike Church, what Almes ſoeuer he hath made, albeit he ſhall ſhed his bloud for the name Chriſt, can by no meanes be ſaued. For neyther Baptiſme, nor large and charitable Almes, nor death it ſelfe, ſuffered for Chriſts ſake, will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle<note place="margin">S. Fulgent. lib. de fide ad Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum.</note> that man who doth not hold the vnity of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> as long as his Hereticall or Schiſmaticall wickednes, which leadeth to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſhall continue in him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3230:24"/>
            <head>A Note of fifty Kings &amp; Queenes of <hi>Great Britany,</hi> accounted Saints, &amp; their Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories celebrated for ſuch, by our Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Forefathers; and this by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Proteſtants themſelues.</head>
            <list>
               <item>S. <hi>Lucius</hi> King of Britany &amp; Martyr. He liued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout<note place="margin">Nauclerus gen. 6. Petr. de Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. l. 1. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> the yeare of Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 192. <hi>Stow &amp; Holinshed in Chron. Cambden. in Brit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Clinta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cus</hi> King of Brecknocke in Wales &amp; Martyr.<note place="margin">Capgrau. in catal. Capgrau<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in catal.</note> About anno 300. <hi>Cambd. in Brit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Wistan</hi> King in Wales and Martyr. About anno 400. <hi>Cambd. in Brit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Ethelbert</hi> King of Kent Confeſſour. About anno 615. <hi>Stow Holinsh. &amp; omnes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bed. l. 1. hiſt.</note>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Edwin</hi> King of Northumberland &amp; Martyr. Anno<note place="margin">Bed. l. 2. Hiſt.</note> 634. <hi>Stow. Cambd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Oſwald</hi> King of Northumberland &amp; Martyr. Anno<note place="margin">Bed. 3. hiſt. Bed. l. 3. c. 24. hiſt. Bed. l. 3. hiſt. c. 18. Bed. l. 4. c. 11. Bed. l. 5. c. 7. Bed. l. 5. Ingulp &amp; alij. Abb. Floriac.</note> 645. <hi>Stow. Cambd. Holinsh. &amp; omnes in Chron.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Oſwine</hi> King of Deiri, vnder the Northumbers, Martyr. Anno 651. <hi>Stow. Cambd. Holinsh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Sigebert</hi> King of the Eaſt-Angles &amp; Martyr. Anno 652. <hi>Stow. Holinshed &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Sebb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> King of the Eaſt-ſaxons Confeſſour. Anno 675. <hi>Stow. Holinsh. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Ceadwall</hi> King of the Weſt-ſaxons Confeſſour, Anno 689. <hi>Stow. Holinsh. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Ethelred</hi> King of the Mercians Confeſſour. Anno<note place="margin">Mar. Scot. Wion.</note> 710. <hi>Stow. Holinsh. Cooper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Alfred</hi> King of Northumberland Confeſſour, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no<note place="margin">Pol. Virg. Math. Weſt. Malmesb.</note> 720. <hi>Stow. Holinsh. Cooper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Inas</hi> King of the Weſt-ſaxons Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nfeſſour Anno
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3230:25"/> 727. <hi>Stow. Cambden. Holinshed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ceolnulph</hi> King of Northumberland Confeſſour.<note place="margin">Bed. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. c. 9. Weſtmon. Sur. tom. 1. Wion. Epit. Bed. Pol. Virg. Weſtmon. Pol. Virgil. Io. Capgrau. Molan. Vincent. in ſpec. Mart. Rom. &amp; alij. Malmesb. l. 1. de Reg. Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on. tom. 10. Annal. Malmesb. Weſtm. Abbo. Flor. Petr. in Catal. Mar. Scot. Abb. Flor. in Hiſtor. Io. leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeus hiſt. Scot. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ol. Virg. l. 6. Sur. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta. Mart. Rom. Sur. &amp; alij. Hect. l. 12. hiſt. Scot. Leſlaeus &amp; alij. Pol virg. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pesfield in hiſt. Regiſtr. Ecc. Windeſor.</note> Anno 737. <hi>Stow. Cooper &amp; alij recent.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Richard</hi> King of Kent Confeſſour. Anno 750. <hi>Camb. Brit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Egbert</hi> King of Northumberland Confeſſour, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 768. <hi>Stow. Cambd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Ethelbert</hi> King of the eaſt Angles Martyr, Anno 793. <hi>Cambd. in his Brit. Hereford.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Fremund</hi> King of the Mercians Martyr, Anno 796. <hi>Stow. Cambd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Kenelmus</hi> King of the Mercians Martyr, Anno 821. <hi>Cambd. Stow. Holinsh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Ethelwold</hi> King of the Northumbers &amp; Martyr An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 790. <hi>Cambd. Stow. Holinsh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Ethelnulph</hi> King of the Weſt-ſaxons Confeſſour, Anno 857. <hi>Stow. Holinsh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Edmund</hi> King of Northumberland Martyr, 870. <hi>Cambd. Brit. in Suffolke. Stow, &amp; omnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Ethelred</hi> King of the Weſt-ſaxons Martyr. Anno 872. <hi>Stow. Holinsh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Alfred</hi> King of the Weſt-ſaxons Confeſſour, An. 899. <hi>Cambd. Stow, &amp; omnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Duffus</hi> King of Scotland &amp; Martyr. Anno 972. <hi>Cambd. Brit. in Murray.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Edgar</hi> Monarke of England Confeſſour, Anno 975. <hi>Stow. Holinsh. &amp; omnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Edward</hi> King of the Weſt-ſaxons Martyr, Anno 978. <hi>Stow. Cambd. &amp; omnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſour K. of England, Anno 1069. <hi>Cambd. Stow, Holinsh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>S. <hi>Malcolme</hi> King of Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>land Confeſſor, Anno 1092. <hi>Cambd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Stow &amp; omnes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>B. <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, at whoſe body in Winde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3230:25"/> very many miracles byn haue wrought. Anno 1479. <hi>Stow. Holinsh. Cambd. in Surrey.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Queenes.<note place="margin">Niceph. Socr. Mart. Rom. In vita S. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wini Reg. Matth. Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Pol. Vir. Vincent. in ſpec. Wion. l. 4 lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni vitae. Beda. l. 4. Tritem. de vit. Illuſtr. Mart. Rom. Bed. l. 4. Weſtmon. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. 640. Bed. l. 4. c. 26. Wion. l. 4. ligni vitae. Bed. l. 4. c. 23. Wion. &amp; alij. Tit. de vir. il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt. Pol. Virg. Capgr. Pol. Virg. Hereb. de faſtis. Sanct. Ethelwerdus in Chron. Matth. Weſt. an. 904. &amp; an<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 901. &amp; 92<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Wion in lig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae.</note>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>S. <hi>Helen</hi> Empreſſe borne at Colcheſter. She liued about Anno 320. <hi>Cambd. in Britan. in Eſſex Stow. &amp; omnes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Ethelburge</hi> Queene of Northumberland. Anno 647. <hi>Cambd. Stow. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Ermenburge</hi> Queene of the Mercians. Anno 654. <hi>Stow. Cambd. &amp; alij.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Chinneburge</hi> Queene of the Weſt-ſaxons. Anno 670. <hi>Cambd. Chron. Brit.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Ermenild</hi> Queene of the Mercians. Anno. 678. <hi>Stow. Cambd.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Audry</hi> Queene of Northumberland. Anno 680. <hi>Cambd. Brit. in Cambridgshire.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Sexburge</hi> Queene of Kent. Anno 686. <hi>Stow. Cambd. in Brit. &amp; alij.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Eanflede</hi> Queene of Northumberland. Anno 690. <hi>Cambd. Brit. Stow. in Cronic.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Hereſwide</hi> Queene of Eaſtangles. Anno 690. <hi>Cambd. Brit. Holinshed &amp; alij.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Edilburge</hi> Queene of Weſt-ſaxons. Anno 840. <hi>Stow. Holinsh. &amp; alij.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Oſith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Queene of the Eaſtangles. Anno 870. <hi>Cambd. in Brit. in Eſſex. &amp; alij omnes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Eue</hi> Queene of the Mercians. Anno 878. <hi>Cambd. in Brit. in Glocest.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Ethelwide</hi> Queene of the Weſt-ſaxons Anno 904. <hi>Stow. Cambd. Holinsh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Eadgith</hi> Queene of Northumberland. Anno 926. <hi>Camb. Brit. Howes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3230:26"/>
                  <item>S. <hi>Algiue</hi> Queene, Mother to King Edgar. Anno 964.<note place="margin">Matth. weſt. anno 943. 955. 974. Pol. Vir. Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulph. Ciceſtr. hiſt. Angl. Hiſt. Scot. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſ Frankford l. 7. Weſt. &amp; Pariſ. an. 1067. Abb. Flor. in eius vita. Mar. Rom Surius &amp; omnes. Matth. Weſt. &amp; Pariſ. Sur. in act. S. Margar. Concert. Eccl. Angl. Didac. de Yepes Ep. Taraconenſ. Hiſtor. de ſchiſ. Anglic.</note> 
                     <hi>Camb. Brit. Stow. Holinsh.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Wilfride</hi> Queene, Wife to King Edgar. Anno 987. <hi>Camb. Brit. Stow. Holinshed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Agatha</hi> Queene, wife to K. Edward the Out-law. Anno 1072. <hi>Camb. Brit. Stow. &amp; alj.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Margaret</hi> Queene of Scotland. Anno. 1092. <hi>Cambd. in Scotland. Stow. &amp; omnes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>S. <hi>Maude</hi> Queene of England. An. 1118. <hi>Camb. Stow. Holinshed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>B. <hi>Mary Stewart</hi> Queene of Scotland. Anno 1587. <hi>Camb. in Britan. &amp; in his</hi> Elizabetha <hi>fuſiùs. D. Willet in his Antilog. of the Engl. Proteſt. to the King, where he wonderfully extolls her for Holines, and truth of Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſides theſe, there are numbred aboue 500. Men &amp; Women, of the Kings, Children, and Bloud Royall of our Iland, that haue in ancient Catholike tymes dedicated themſelues to God, in holy Religion: &amp; this by the testimony of our owne Protestant writers.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3230:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
